<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Living The Dream</title>
    <atom:link href="http://azat.co/blog/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link>
    <link>http://azat.co/blog</link>
    <description>Azat's personal weblog</description>
    <pubDate>Wed, 04 Jun 2014 15:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
    <generator>Wintersmith - https://github.com/jnordberg/wintersmith</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <item>
      <title>Fast Food Paleo Style</title>
      <link>http://azat.co/blog/blog/fast-food-paleo-style/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Jun 2014 15:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://azat.co/blog/blog/fast-food-paleo-style/</guid>
      <author></author>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Oftentimes, we are on the go, have to travel or just want to indulge in the staple of the &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Standard_American_Diet&quot;&gt;standard American diet&lt;/a&gt; (SAD) — fast food. Personally, I find most fast food restaurants convenient. They are quick, offer a good value and have  predictable quality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://photos-h.ak.instagram.com/hphotos-ak-xfp1/10354485_1503576039861887_341941421_n.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is what I order:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Salad with proteins (chicken or beef) and without croutons/bread/corn/grains&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Burgers without buns, some places call them “wrapped in lettuces”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://photos-a.ak.instagram.com/hphotos-ak-xaf1/917265_459351284170824_997640800_n.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There’s nothing wrong with treating yourself once in a while to a small side of french fries (with garlic, yum!) or a smoothie/milk shake. Even Mark Sisson says that we should’t be hard on ourselves all the time (&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.marksdailyapple.com/8020-principle/&quot;&gt;80/20 rule&lt;/a&gt;). Just be careful not to make it a daily (or for some even a weekly trip can be dangerous) meal!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://scontent-a.cdninstagram.com/hphotos-xpa1/t51.2885-15/927868_498328226951733_1006424496_n.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My favorite joints are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.superdupersf.com/&quot;&gt;SuperDuper Burgers&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Chipotle&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Panera&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mixt Greens / Chop’t&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;McDonald’s&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://distilleryimage9.ak.instagram.com/6e9bcd02a1f411e39703123fed77b305_8.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Road to Ensenada</title>
      <link>http://azat.co/blog/blog/road-to-ensenada/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 May 2014 09:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://azat.co/blog/blog/road-to-ensenada/</guid>
      <author></author>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Ensenada, Baja California, Mexico is only 9-11 hours driving from the Bay Area. It’s a relatively large port city that serves as tourist cruises port of call. It has nice Pacific Ocean views and great seafood. The commerce is thriving on the US border with street vendors, acrobats and windshield window washers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://scontent-a.cdninstagram.com/hphotos-prn/t51.2885-15/1963154_1423660997884988_706200877_n.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;
Hard not to love this place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://photos-c.ak.instagram.com/hphotos-ak-frc/891333_242328732618938_1830829158_n.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;
Much aho — extra garlic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://photos-d.ak.instagram.com/hphotos-ak-prn/928226_376930915779707_1057103337_n.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;
Extremely fresh and meaty oysters at the marina cafe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://photos-e.ak.instagram.com/hphotos-ak-prn/1170533_630359280365420_1087288531_n.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;
An hour spent manivering between hustling people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;640&quot; height=&quot;360&quot; src=&quot;//www.youtube.com/embed/jKRsCWhszzw&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
The Road to Ensenada by Lyle Lovett&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Crimean War</title>
      <link>http://azat.co/blog/blog/the-crimean-war/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 May 2014 14:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://azat.co/blog/blog/the-crimean-war/</guid>
      <author></author>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In lieu of &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.cnn.com/SPECIALS/2014/ukraine/&quot;&gt;events&lt;/a&gt; that started in December 2013 and still are happening in Ukraine (originally part of the Russian Empire and then the USSR), events that resulted in Crimea becoming a part of Russian Federation, I picked up a book about the &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Crimean_War&quot;&gt;Crimean War&lt;/a&gt; of 1853-56. The book turned out to be a longer than I expected, about 600 pages, but I enjoyed every single page of it because the author gives such a good geopolitical picture of what was going on before and after the war, as well as the atmosphere and trends of the major part of the 19th century. The book is called &lt;strong&gt;The Crimean War: A History by Orlando Figes&lt;/strong&gt; and it’s available in &lt;a href=&quot;http://amzn.to/1krSGWg&quot;&gt;Kindle on Amazon.com&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I vaguely remember the very brief coverage of the Crimean War during my high school history class: something about the heroism of soldiers and Russian backwards technologies. It was good to look at the events from the British author’s point of view. Here are the things the surprised and impressed me the most:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Crimean War was the first modern war which involved heavy industrialized manufacturing — at least on the side of France and the British Empire — and the attrition warfare closely resembled World War I.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The public opinion was the major factor influencing French, British and Russian rulers in entering and ending the conflict — just like now!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The war started for many geopolitical (weakening of the Ottoman Empire), populist (the British press was very anti-Russian) and personal agendas (Nicholas I believed in the holy mission and the third Rome idea, and Napoleon III needed a victory to increase his influence).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Nobody liked the poor Turks, not even their French and British allies.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There were highly effective and flamboyant French &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zouave&quot;&gt;Zouave troops&lt;/a&gt; after which the American Civil War Zouaves were modeled just a few years later.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Interestingly enough, not many things have changed over 160 years in terms of the influence of public opinion and attempts at controlling it. Back then, the British Empire had &lt;em&gt;free&lt;/em&gt; press, but there was some censorship of photography and in the army, e.g., the officers writing about the horrors of the first winter were considered traitors by their commanders. Orlando writes that the French emperor Napoleon III had spies everywhere and a tight grip on the press with censorship. The same things were true for the Russian Tsar Nicholas I.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One thing that changed dramatically was the speed of communication. The news traveled very slowly during the Crimean War — it took a few days in the beginning of the conflict for the news to reach its destination until the telegraph line was laid under the Black Sea (for the allies). Now, we can just sit in the comfort of our homes, scanning Twitter with the #Ukraine hashtag, and getting real-time updates, photos and even live streams of events miles away!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;PS: Twitter stops indexing search results after a couple of days, so you might want to try Storify for historical searches, e.g., &lt;a href=&quot;https://storify.com/search?q=ukraine&quot;&gt;https://storify.com/search?q=ukraine&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>My First Post</title>
      <link>http://azat.co/blog/blog/my-first-post/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Apr 2014 15:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://azat.co/blog/blog/my-first-post/</guid>
      <author></author>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I’m starting my personal blog and this is its first post. This blog unlike webapplog will contain &lt;strong&gt;zero coding&lt;/strong&gt;, and lots of musings, instagrams and rants.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you might guess that blog is built with Node.js-powered Wintersmith static site generator. The Ghost just can’t compete with the simplier set up that Wintersmith has.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>